Guide to the Murray Stein Artifact Collection on Computer History, circa 1940-circa 1990 MS0656.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Murray Stein artifact collection on computer history
circa 1940-circa 1990
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Stein, Murray
MS0656.UA
7 Linear Feet
Collection contains an assortment of old computer parts, calculators, reel-to-reel information tape. Examples of the development of wafers and the computer chip, a board from the 1952 Univac, mounted exhibit of the evolution of tubes (used before resisters and compactors), and other physical examples of the evolution of the computer.
Box 3
Box 2
Box 1
Box 5
Box 4
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated to University Archives by Murray Stein in 1997.
Biographical Note
Murray Stein is an engineering graduate from The George Washington University, class of 1949. He is currently retired.
An oral history done with Mr. Stein can be found in MS0371, the Oral History Collection.
This note was written in 2005.
Collection Scope and Content
Collection contains an assortment of artifacts related to the evolution of the computer, such as old computer parts, calculators, reel-to-reel information tape.
Also included are examples of the development of wafers and the computer chip, a board from the 1952 Univac, mounted exhibit of the evolution of tubes (used before resisters and compactors), and other physical examples of the evolution of the computer.
Additionally, there is a short written work called, "A History of Computing" (n.d.) by Murray Stein.
Collection note
The items have been given generic descriptions in this finding aid, since it is difficult to know what the parts are because they were not tagged when they were donated to University Archives. The original list follows: A Board of mounted tubes Computer hard drive Small hand bag Merchant mechanical computer Computer tapes (3)Wooden boards (small) Friden automatic calculators Monroe merchant computer Track tape head Qualitron calculator Calculator parts (2)Bowmar calculator Super brain calculator Calculator tubes Panasonic solar calculator Director Two calculator Data cartridge Computer memories Pascal calculator Air navigation dead reckoning compass Micromatic slide rule Slide rule Pocket book of Engineering formulasComputer tubes (3)Unidentified parts Abacus sorban Board with computer chips (3)Mechanical electromagnetic relaysComputer core memory IC flip flop Data communication board Part of the super computer of the 1980's and 90's.
Computers; Washington (D.C.); Univac computer; George Washington University; Stein, Murray; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae
- Large glass tube, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  General note
  Item labeled #4
- Small glass tube, General Electric FG-67, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Item labeled #5
- Switch I, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Item labeled #6
- 1.2 Volt regulator, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Item labeled #7
- Unidentified chip, on back, IERC P006B, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Item labeled #8
- Intel I 486 chip, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Item labeled #9
- Unidentified part, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Item labeled #10
- Marchant mechanical computer, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Item labeled #11
- Small gray plaque that says "THINK" made by IBM, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Item labeled #14
- Friden calculator, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Item labeled #15
- Friden automatic calculator user's manual, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Item labeled #16
- Artifacts, undated (Box 2)
- Abbreviated processing sequence for a solar cell (attached to a wooden board), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Item labeled #1; The sequence begins from left to right starting with sand, single crystal boule, raw wafer, polished wafer, patterned wafer, 1st level etching, final device
- Wooden board composed of various integr scales, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Item labeled #2; Small scale integr less than 100 devices (SSI), medium scale integr 100s of devices (MSI), large scale integr 10,000s of devices (LSI), very large scale integr 100,000s of devises (VLSI), integrated circuits, chips
- Circuit board from a univac, with 31 circuits and tubes, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Item labeled #3
- Tubes and circuits on a wooden board, 31 pieces, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Item labeled #12
- Evolution of the size of computer chips from 1 inch to 12 inches, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Item labeled #13
- Artifacts, undated (Box 3)
- Black oxide on paper (one quarter), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Item labeled #17
- Brown oxide on plastic (one quarter), 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Item labeled #18
- Hard disk, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Item labeled #19
- Computer tapes, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Item labeled #20
- Vari-Punch machine & box made by Varifab Inc. in the U.S.A., undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Item labeled #21
- Stein tape No-0001, IBM data processing, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Item labeled #22
- Computer part, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Item labeled #23
- Punch cards, 15 pieces, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Item labeled #24
- EK-5G Computer part made in Taiwan, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Item labeled #25
- Unidentified part, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Item labeled #26
- Computer chips and 2 rocks, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Item labeled #27
- Computer chart, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Item labeled #28
- Artifacts, undated (Box 4)
- Micromatic slide rule, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Item labeled #29
- Slide rule, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Item labeled #30
- Tung sol electron tube with box, delay relay amperite with box, computer chip kit, and computer chip, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Item labeled #31
- CD Rom, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Item labeled #32
- Floppy disk, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Item labeled #33
- Complex data communications board, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Item labeled #34
- Air navigation/dead reckoning computer, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Item labeled #35
- Circuit board chip, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Item labeled #36
- IBM circuit board chip panels, 4 pieces, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Item labeled #37
- Ferroxoplate-slide of a circuit board made by Towne Laboratories, Inc., undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Item labeled #38
- Data Cartridges-DC 2000 mini data cartridge, DC 300A data cartridges, 3 pieces, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Item labeled #39
- Encased chips and circuits from Burroughs Corporation, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Item labeled #40
- Transistor made by IBM, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Item labeled #41
- Large green computer circuit board, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Item labeled #42
- Core memory Larc II, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Item labeled #43
- Wristwatch made by Quintel in Hong Kong, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Item labeled #44
- Wooden board with ram, rom, prom, eprom, and eaprom, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Item labeled #45
- Abacus/soroban, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Item labeled #46
- Babbage analytical engine based on punch cards and gears, 1833 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Item labeled #47
- Calculator made by Bowmar, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Item labeled #48
- Solar calculator made by Panasonic, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Item labeled #49
- Calculator made by Eldorado Electrodata Corporation, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Item labeled #50
- Calculator made by Bomar and inscribed on it is "super brain", undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Item labeled #51
- Calculator made by Radio Shack, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Item labeled #52
- Artifacts, undated (Box 5)
- Electronic calcu-counter operation card and calculator, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Item labeled #53
- Pascal calculator, 1642 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Item labeled #54
- Molesworth's pocket book of engineering formula, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Item labeled #55
- B5500 Flip-Flop 2070, 2 pieces, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Item labeled #56
- An all in one slide rule/calculator and desk name plaque, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Item labeled #57
- Ionic reusity meter, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Item labeled #58
- Medium sized computer chip, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Item labeled #59
- Unidentified object made by IBM, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Item labeled #60
- Compilation of computer chips and parts, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Item labeled #61
- Calculator, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Item labeled #62
- Calculator, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Item labeled #63
- Mark I (mechanical) electromagnetic relays, 4 pieces in all, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Item labeled #64
- Pascal's adder calculator, 1642 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Item labeled #65
- Monograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Item labeled #66
- Plastic cases with glass slides, computer chips, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Item labeled #67
- Unidentified parts, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Item labeled #68; 3 pieces
- Cassette tape, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  Item labeled #69
- Unidentified parts, 3 pieces, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  Item labeled #70; 3 pieces
- Unidentified parts, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Item labeled #71
- Unidentified part made by Control Data Corporation, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  Item labeled #72
- Unidentified part made in Japan, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  Item labeled #73
- Early form of computer chip, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  Item labeled #74
- Broken computer chip, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  Item labeled #75
- "History of Computing", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  11-page essay "A History of Computing," by Stein, which explains some of the items in the collection